So let's begin another
speed run game incoming at 2108 GM 109.
All right, so we're going Sicilian.
And
as I explained
two games ago, I've made kind of an
interesting executive decision, which is
basically past 2100 to play my actual
opening repertoire. So rather than going
with the accelerated Dragon, which we've
had quite a bit of um I'm going to
revert back to the Najdorf and I think
it's a win-win. I'll introduce the basic
ideas of the Najdorf and obviously it's
an opening that I know really really
well. So you'll kind of get another
feather in your cap. Now the previous
time we faced Bishop B5 check and I got
completely outplayed and almost lost the
game. It was a really fascinating video.
By the time you're watching this on
YouTube, that video should be up
already.
And here our opponent opts for the main
line, which is called the open Sicilian.
Of course we take on D4.
We develop the knight to F6 and here
there is a major fork in the road. First
of all, white does not have to play
knight C3
but does so in like 99% of cases.
Here there is a major fork in the road.
The Najdorf is the most popular
response. It is followed by the sort of
second tier Sicilians. The Rauzer or the
classical Sicilian is knight C6. And of
course the Dragon, the traditional
Dragon is G6. But that's not all. There
are a couple of other moves, more
obscure moves. E6 is the Scheveningen,
which I also talked about in that other
video.
Because we actually got that structure
through a different line.
But that's still not it. There is even
the obscure move Bishop D7, which at one
moment was quite popular and there's the
Keres Attack variation, which is the
immediate E5. I'll show that line a
little bit after the game because E5
kind of fails on a tactical front. But
in this game we play the Najdorf A6,
named after Polish Argentinian GM Miguel
Najdorf, who breathed the most life into
the actual opening. And since this is
the first time I'm playing the Najdorf,
the the body of theory that
could be that could be talked about is
is way way way too vast for even a
10-hour long video. So I'm going to have
to restrict myself essentially to what
our opponent plays because books have
been written simply on this one line.
White has seven or eight uh incredibly
theoretical and dangerous continuations
that range from Bishop G5 to the Fischer
Attack with Bishop C4 uh to more
positional moves like A4 and Bishop B2.
I'll give you kind of the the general
menu, maybe try to give you a flavor for
some of black's typical ideas after the
game. But here we are facing what's
called the English Attack. And the
English Attack is defined by this move
F3 that white plays for two purposes.
The first is obvious, white is securing
the E4 pawn. But the second is to
prepare what's called the English
Attack. It's named after uh several
English grandmasters who were kind of
the first to play this system regularly
after black castles king side. White's
point is to run the pawns up the board,
G4, G5, H4, etc. And that is why white
starts off by playing F3.
Here another fork in the road for black.
The Scheveningen structure is reached if
we play E6. But the type of Najdorf that
I personally like to play a lot more and
I have a lot more experienced with that
structure. Does anybody know what the
other main move is other than E6? Which
leads to a fundamentally different type
of position. These two lines are have
have not a lot in common, believe it or
not. And the other move of course is E5,
immediately attacking the knight.
And if you're seeing all of this for the
first time, if you're a newer player
watching this on YouTube, I would if I
were you, I wouldn't worry too much
about sort of trying to understand the
point of each move because this is like
opening theory that's been known for
many many years and it's hard for me to
explain all of this from like first
principles. So what you should
focus on right now is that this is
opening theory. I'll contextualize this
after the game, but for now we just need
to get to a fresh position. So here
following E5, we need to secure the D5
square. That is of course the main
positional drawback of all Najdorfs
where you play E5.
And so it makes sense to bring the
bishop out to E6, securing the D5 square
and preventing white's bishop from
developing to C4. Now we continue
developing our king side Bishop E7.
Typically white plays Queen D2 in order
to prepare long castles and that's why
the Najdorf is such a fascinating
opening. In many lines there is opposite
side castling. This is the most kind of
traditional Najdorfy type line where
black attacks on the queen side, white
attacks on the king side. Now let's see
who watches my stream regularly because
in this position the main move by a
country mile is knight BD7, G4 and then
B5. But there is a much more obscure
move that I really really like to play.
I've played it successfully for
right about a year now in in online
blitz. And this is a move which was
popular about 15 years ago
and I have found that even top players
are completely clueless against this
line. Because yes, black is worse if
white plays perfectly, but if white
makes even one small misstep, this line
can lead to absolute crushing defeat in
20 moves. And the move I'm talking about
is not weird per se. I think it makes
sense when you see it, but it might seem
awkward because we've already played A6.
And A6 seems to prepare B5 and that's
the main way to attack.
But the move that I want to focus on is
actually A5. I've played it over the
board. I've played it hundreds of times
online and our opponent clearly still
versed in this line. Bishop B5 is one of
the best moves. Now the point of Bishop
B5 is to prevent black from playing A4,
which would kick the knight to this
ungodly square on A1.
But the drawback of putting the bishop
on B5 is that it can be vulnerable to
attack by the B8 knight. And here you
simply have to know the ideas of the
line in order to play it successfully.
So here the move is knight A6, which is
probably not a move that you would
arrive at if you were looking at this
for the first time. You would probably
be inclined to develop the knight to C6,
but there is a very concrete point of
knight A6 and that is to drop the knight
back to C7 in order to dislodge this
bishop on B5. And if it is successfully
dislodged, then we can continue storming
the queen side with A4.
Alternatively, if white leaves the
bishop on B5 after knight C7, we get the
bishop pair. And once the knight leaves
C3, this is one of the main Najdorf
ideas across almost all variations. You
should be aware that this move often is
in black's favor particularly if you
have the bishop pair. What am I talking
about? I'm of course I'm talking about
the central breakthrough D5, which
makes sense positionally because it
eradicates the weak square on D5. Right?
That is the way that you eradicate
weaknesses. You like push a pawn and
change the structure and D5 is no longer
a weak square. So D5 is a very kind of
seminal idea in this particular
variation of the Najdorf as well as in
most uh
variations of the Najdorf, both
positional and tactical.
King B1. So that is a good move.
And of course now we follow up with
knight to C7, posing white with a
dilemma. And this is one of the lines in
which white has to know really like four
or five moves of relatively obscure
theory
not just to get a better position, but
if white doesn't know it, then white
often ends up like much much worse or or
even lost. So I'm banking on the fact
that our opponent isn't like
wildly well versed in theory. I played
this against Fabby in a titled Tuesday
game and got a winning position out of
the opening.
So it's a little bit risky. I will
reveal like some of white's best
continuations even though it works
against my interest after the game.
But let's see how this turns out. I
still think that you can play this line
successfully um with black definitely in
online blitz because even if white plays
down the best line, it's still very very
hard to play practically.
Yeah, so here the main move is actually
Bishop E3 to B6.
Which
is not necessarily an an obvious move.
It
Well, it sort of is if you if you
understand what you're looking for.
Bishop B6 pins the knight to the queen
and seems to permanently prevent the
problem of knight takes B5. But in
response to Bishop B6, black has I would
call it a sexy move.
Black can unpin the knight by moving the
queen and shifting it over from D8 over
to B8.
Queen D8 to B8. And sometimes in that
line the queen can make its home on A7
in certain situations. But the main
point of Queen B8 is to renew the threat
of knight takes B5. So in in some ways
I'm trying to like explain opening
theory, which is hard to do with an
opening as tactical as the Najdorf. And
this is a a small taste of why I did not
recommend the Najdorf to newer players,
right? At the start of the speed run.
The accelerated Dragon is a much more
accessible Sicilian. It's a little bit
less theoretical and it's easier to
understand like why you're putting the
pieces on the squares that you're
putting them. Almost the placement of
almost every piece can be explained a
priori, whereas the Najdorf is just such
a tactical line that a lot of moves
they can be explained. You can
understand why they're played, but
largely you have to understand them
through the lens of studying a bunch of
variations and then the move starts to
kind of make sense. I don't know if that
explanation itself makes sense, but
hopefully it gives you a little bit of
context. Okay, so here I have to
remember the move because
we have two options. The first is to
push D5 and that has to be calculated.
The second is to bring the rook up to
A6, which is another very typical idea
in this line and kick this bishop away
from B6.
Now the benefit of playing rook A6 is
that if the bishop simply moves back to
E3, we play B5 and we win the game. The
bishop on A4 is trapped.
So after rook A6
what is white planning? What is our
opponent going to do? Well, of course
white can take on C7, but generally
that's kind of a win for us. Like we
want the bishop pair. We want to force
white to take on C7.
Now after rook A6, I guess there's also
the move queen to E3 in order to protect
the bishop on B6.
That actually might be the best line.
I'm pretty impressed with uh
how our opponent is handling handling
this line. He knows a lot more than than
even some GMs. So, I'm pretty sure rook
A6 queen E3 is to be avoided, which
leaves us with the other move D5.
Now, we don't care about the A5 pawn.
In almost no cases are we concerned that
white's going to take on A5 because that
merely helps our attacking cause. It
opens up the A file, and most of the
time white can't even get away with
taking on A5 because there's like too
many hanging minor pieces. So, I'm
pretty sure that D5 is the better option
here.
I will be honest, I don't know this
position like I'm out of book. But, D5
feels A, very very exciting, B, in the
spirit of the position, and C,
I think confronts our opponent with
difficult practical problems. So,
uh on a basic level, this move works as
follows. It opens up the dark squared
bishop, and there are enough defenders
on the D5 square. So, we have 1 2 3 uh
minor pieces guarding it. White has 1 2
3 four pieces attacking it, but because
the queen is in front, after E takes D5
knight takes D5 knight takes D5 knight
takes D5, you know, it's like the fact
that queen
is among the primary attackers overrides
the fact that there are more attackers
than defenders. So, obviously their
queen takes D5 is not possible because
white drops the queen.
So, of course, white can win this pawn
by first taking on C7. White can play
bishop takes knight eliminating a
defender, and then white can grab the
pawn with uh his own pawn. And in that
position, well, in that position we had
the tactical move rook D8 in order to
recover the pawn. Our opponent takes on
D5 with a knight. Okay, we don't have
much of a choice here. Let's take back
with a knight. And after ED, it makes
the most sense to take on D5 with a
knight because
if we take with the bishop, that doesn't
come with tempo. And remember, again,
our general approach here is to drive
the bishop out of B6, and already things
are getting a little bit difficult for
white because again, if white plays
bishop F2, we move the pawn up to B5,
and the game ends immediately. And I
have won countless games exactly in this
kind of way where white's just sort of
unsuspectingly moving pieces, and
suddenly these minor pieces are actually
incredibly vulnerable to to a pawn
storm. So, I already think that white
made a rash move. I think knight takes
D5 was kind of an impulsive reaction.
I'm pretty sure that bishop takes C7 has
to be played. And now I'm starting to
remember that there's like a queen sac
line there that I'll show after the
game.
The fact that our opponent is starting
to think already tells me that he senses
that he's done something wrong.
Queen F2. Okay, maybe not. Maybe this is
still theory, and I'm totally wrong.
That's totally possible.
Queen F2 makes the most sense.
Okay, now we should not rush to grab
this bishop. I know that in general, I
explained that we want to remove this
bishop, but if we take it, the queen
replaces it, and the queen is then going
to be pretty hard to dislodge from B6.
Let's see if we can play for maximum
here because if we force this bishop
away from B6, then we will in fact be
able to play B5. So, what are the
alternatives to knight takes B6? Well,
of course, one of the reasons that we
play A5 is to guarantee the option of
rook A6. So, let's consider rook to A6.
Okay, so we hit the bishop. The bishop
has to move. It'll probably drop back to
C5 in that line. Rook A6 bishop C5.
Then, we should not take on C5 because
white recaptures with a knight, and uh
so hits our rook, hits our bishop.
That's awful. So, after rook A6 bishop
C5, I think it's important to notice
that the bishop on E7 is protected by
the knight. So, I think we can actually
straight away go B5.
And if white plays bishop takes E7, then
we can play knight takes E7. But,
unfortunately, in that final position,
can anybody spy a tactical defensive
move for white? In that final position
after rook A6 bishop C5 B5 takes takes,
and then knight C5.
Yeah, knight C5 is the move. Exactly,
very good. Uh Misha.
And then after knight C5,
I'm trying to figure out if we can
pin the knight with a move like queen to
A7,
then white plays bishop takes B5. Things
get very messy. So, let's do this again.
Rook A6 bishop C5
B5
bishop takes E7. Can we play B takes A4
instead? Maybe that's a good
alternative.
Things get very very messy there.
But, it actually seems to me like we
can.
Or at least we might be able to
sacrifice the exchange for a long-term
attack on the king's on the queen's
side.
Technically, this side of the board is
still the queen side even though white's
king is located there.
Yeah, rook A6 is too juicy not to play.
Takes takes. Do we have any interesting
options there? I don't love black's
position
after the trade on B6 just because
we kind of stagnate on the king side.
And this knight is a very important
attacker. Sometimes it can jump to B4 or
C3. So, we want to avoid giving it up if
possible.
Okay, let me do a little bit more
calculation silently.
And don't worry, like I'll explain all
of this after the game,
but I just have to think
seriously
because the lines are incredibly
incredibly complex even for me. I mean,
this is the no joke. Absolute no joke.
You can lose this with one little
inaccuracy.
Calculating an insane line.
So, there there there. Bishop has to
move. Where does it go? It goes to C5
though.
Okay, then we play BC queen takes C2
rook C6.
That looks very dubious, but it could be
rewarding. So, rook A6 bishop C5 B5
takes takes knight C5.
We can play rook C6.
Then, white plays knight E6 FE bishop B3
A4.
White plays bishop B3 immediately. We
can play Mhm, can't quite work it out.
Okay, but let's go rook A6. I feel like
we have to take up the gauntlet. I've
I've sunk way too much time into this
move to not play rook A6 at this point.
I've sunk I I I've sunk sunk way way too
much time to then just play knight takes
B6.
But, I I'm still not sure what I'm going
to do after bishop C5 B5 bishop takes
E7.
Because the option of sacking the
exchange there is very enticing, but it
leads to just complete and utter chaos.
That's unevaluable. Like, it's
impossible to say if black is winning,
black is losing, but my gut is that it's
unsound. I feel like that exchange sac
is unsound. So, I think we're going to
go for the simpler option of recapturing
on E7 uh provided that white finds all
of this, which is still not a given.
Absolutely not a given that white finds
bishop C5. I think some people would
panic and like play rook takes D5. Very
typical panic reaction when you see that
the B pawn is going to advance on the
next move.
Um another panicky move would be like
knight C5. Oh, let's try to complicate
things, but knight C5 just loses the
game,
and uh it loses because after rook takes
B6 knight takes E6, another complicated
question for you guys. Does anybody see
black's winning move there? So, if white
plays knight C5 rook takes B6, and
knight takes E6, what's the winning
intermezzo?
Consider the placement of the rook on B6
and what it's doing. Yeah, it's actually
knight C3 check, and then you take the
rook on D1 attacking the queen.
It's not rook takes E6 because that
leaves the knight on C5 exposed,
and it's actually not F takes E6 because
white plays rook takes D5 removing the
defender, and the queen makes contact
with the rook.
So, just crazy lines there. Our opponent
is probably calculating them as well.
And again, I just want to make sure that
particularly newer players who are
watching this, don't be discouraged if
you're feeling lost right now, or you're
feeling like uh what am I supposed to
learn from all this? I don't get what
you're saying. This is normal. Like,
this is what the Najdorf is like. And
just be patient. Try to pick out like
what you can. If I'm saying a line, and
you want to follow it on your own board,
that's fine. You can pause the video and
make the moves on the board uh to help
yourself visualize, but just try to
follow as best you can, and I'll try to
give as much detail as possible
afterward. Okay, so, um we're going to
go and nor am I trying to deliberately
like obfuscate my thinking. This is just
This is genuinely incredibly complex,
and our opponent is dodging all of the
minefields beautifully. So, we have to
play knight takes E7. And here, I don't
even spend any time considering B takes
A4. This was the exchange sac that I was
talking about. It was B takes A4 bishop
takes F8 and A takes B3. There, I think
white has a ridiculously advanced
winning move C4. We'll see if I
evaluated this correctly after the game.
Knight C5. Okay. So,
mhm, very important position. Now,
taking the bishop here doesn't seem
promising. White plays knight takes A6
and then evacuates the knight back
through C5.
We can play rook to B6, which is the
move that I was trying to figure out for
a while, but white plays bishop B3
there, and we don't trap the bishop
because the bishop has an exit point. It
can just take black's bishop on E6.
What are the other options available to
us? Well, we could say, "Okay, we can
see the alignment of the knight and the
queen, and we could try to pin the
knight with queen A7 or even queen to
B6."
Okay, what is black white going to do
there? Well, white's probably going to
drop the bishop back to B3. This is sort
of the bailout option. Like, to play
queen A7.
If queen A7, white can actually play
bishop takes B5. So, if we make one of
those moves, it's probably queen B6, and
I don't love the resulting position, but
it's a good bailout option to have in
our pocket. The other interesting option
is to play rook to C6.
And the point of rook to c6 is that it
targets the knight on c5. White still
has to play Bishop b3 there, I would
imagine.
And there, maybe we can target the
knight again with a move like Queen b6
or Queen a7, same type of idea. The
except the point is we we send the rook
to c6 first
as opposed to playing Queen b6 first,
then the rook is very awkwardly stuck on
a6.
So, from that perspective, I like the
look of rook c6. And if after rook c6,
white takes the knight first, we take
back with a pawn. Bishop b3 a4 traps the
bishop. So, it also sets, I think, a
nice trap. Let's go with rook c6.
We need to watch our clock here, down to
5 minutes, but I think that's enough
time.
Bishop takes a2 is a thought, but I
don't see what it does after King takes
a2. Okay, our opponent is playing
really, really magnificently. So, now
I'm going to have to hunker down and
play a little faster. So, what do we do
now?
Well, now we have another dilemma,
because if we take on b3, we double
white's pawns, very likely, which
probably is the best move. We can also
play Queen b6 straight away.
But why would we succumb to damage of
our own? Like white will play Bishop
takes c6, f takes c6, and can drop the
knight back to e4.
Um unfortunately, the
bad luck, the queen, had it been on e3,
would have been indefensible by the
knight. As it stands, knight e4 knight
c3 guards the queen. So, we can't win
the knight.
Bishop c4 blunders the fork on b7. This
is another mental note that you have to
make, forkable squares. Knight d7 is a
move you have to watch for, regardless
of what you do.
So, I think we should play Bishop takes
b3. Now, you might say, "Well, what
about knight d7 here?" But it fails
tactically. Knight d7 here, Bishop takes
c2 check. It can be a bit hard to count
the material in the resulting position,
but it is winning for black. Just trust
me on that.
So, white's going to recapture this
bishop with what? My guess is a takes b3
is the most natural move.
But not necessarily
the move that a newer player might
choose. A newer player might be very
concerned about doubling the pawns and
might recapture with the knight, which
would have allowed us to fuel the fire
of our attack with a4. Now, we want to
attack the knight. How do we do it?
Well, again, there's Queen b6, and this
time it's a bailout option, because
Queen b6 basically forces an endgame.
Knight d3, we can trade queens, and the
endgame is probably about equal.
But are there ways to extract more juice
from the placement of this knight? Well,
there is, I think, a nice way to do
that. And that's to double the rooks on
c8, which might strike you as like an
unexpected move. You might be like, "Oh,
where is the rook on f8?" Well, there
is.
And I think we should put it to use.
And I think we should play rook f2 c8.
And attack the knight on c5. In so
doing, we're taking the sting out of the
move knight d7, which still might strike
you as a bit scary, and it scares me a
little bit. But now, knight d7 doesn't
really do anything. We play Queen c7, we
triple on the c-file. Remember that once
that happens, c2 starts to hang.
And then the knight on d7 is stranded.
So, intuitively, that doesn't seem
dangerous to me.
So, white has to move this knight. b4,
we just play a takes b4, so there's no
way to defend it.
And legendary triple stack. So, white's
probably going to move it back to d3.
And in that position, we have yet
another decision that we have to make,
fun times. What decision do we have to
make after knight d3? Like,
specifically, what move do we have to
decide whether to play or not to play?
Two rooks for the queen. So, we can grab
the pawn on c2. Obviously, white's going
to recapture. We take on c2, and white
plays King takes c2. Now, I have a very
strong intuition
about whether or not to go for that
line.
But I'm curious to poll the crowd. Like,
ask yourself right now,
this is a good test of your intuition,
and this can help you develop better
instincts.
Do you feel like going rook takes c2? Do
you think it's a good call practically?
Or should we keep the initiative and
play a move like, you know, h6 or maybe
f6, and just keep the pressure going on
c2? And I'm not saying that I'm right,
but I feel pretty strongly that I know
the answer.
So, my intuition is to absolutely play
rook takes c2 for two chief reasons. The
first is that, remember, we get an
additional pawn, which may sound
unimportant, but a pawn and a queen for
two rooks is better than just queen for
two rooks. All of that is a moot point.
Let's leave that all aside until after
the game, because our opponent has
surprised us with knight d7.
Now, don't fall for rook takes c2 here,
because white simply plays Queen takes
c2, classic desperado sac, and our queen
hangs.
So, we have to go Queen c7.
Now, clearly, I missed something here,
because I don't think our opponent would
be going for this move
without seeing a follow-up, because the
knight really is,
you know, stranded amongst the trees.
But we need to be very patient and very
mindful of tactics here, because rook to
d8 actually succumbs to this crazy idea,
knight takes e5, and white uses the back
rank mate to evacuate the knight. So,
just actually incredible idea by our
opponent.
What does that tell us? Well, that
basically tells me that
the biggest problem for black here is
the back rank weakness.
So, a move that I would be seriously
considering, particularly in time
pressure, is either h6 or f6. f6
kills two birds with one stone, because
it secures the e5 pawn. But conversely,
f6 weakens the king a little bit. So,
it's very hard to decide between h6 and
f6. We don't want to go g6, because it
creates a hole lot of six.
So, I'm really struggling to decide
here.
We're down to 3 minutes. We also could
ignore and just attack on the queen
side. But given the time pressure, I
think h6 is a very wise decision.
I'm going to go with my gut here.
And my gut is to play h6. My gut is to
not weaken our king any further than it
needs to be weakened.
h6 feels right to me. We'll check with
the engine after the game.
As I said in the previous game, it's not
like I have access to some hidden store
of information that helps me make these
decisions. They are hard decisions
for anybody to make, even a GM. Now, I
think we have a bit of a respite.
Now, it doesn't make sense to attack
this knight, because if we shift our
rook to d8, well, that fails tactically
to knight f6. I actually think that the
situation has quieted down temporarily,
which gives us a tempo, which we can use
to further our interests on the queen
side.
So, I think we we should just continue
our attack, right? We should play a4.
We shouldn't take our eyes off the main
goal of this position, which is still to
go after white's king.
And we're dangerously low on time.
Now, what else am I noticing here? Well,
I'm looking at the e5 pawn and making
sure that, you know, white can't capture
it. So, I calculated knight e5, Queen e5
anyway. That doesn't work. b4 by our
opponent. And I just realized that I
completely forgot that gave him the c5
square. That was a bad move. a4 was a
bad move.
Immediately spotted by our opponent, but
maybe we can play a3 and try to justify
it.
Maybe we can play a3 and try to justify
it. No, that was a very, very bad move.
I completely forgot that white gets the
c5 square. I might have to play a little
bit more silently
last part of the game here, because
we're getting low on time.
So, a3 knight c5.
Yeah, clearly, this guy is a GM hunter,
because
yours truly is getting outplayed here.
Okay, so maybe knight f5 knight d4, that
idea does come to mind. Knight g6 is a
more conservative way to do that.
But
uh
crap, that was a really bad move. I
completely forgot about that.
Okay, so let's try to re- reshuffle our
pieces a little bit.
Ah, rook c4, he's actually got knight
b6. JESUS.
OH, WAIT, WE have a cool line there.
It doesn't work. Are you kidding me?
Man, I can't seem to get anything to
work here.
Okay, let's go knight f5, which I which
I should have just played on the
previous move. I mean, I I don't have no
idea why I didn't see this.
We should have just got knight f5 here,
and then the knight would have continued
to be stranded on d7. Just kicking
myself for that mental lapse.
Very, very poor uh poor poor move by me.
But still, the position remains like
ultra playable. I don't even think black
is worse Well,
maybe black is worse at this point, but
not much worse, that's for sure. Because
our king is now fully safe.
Yeah, the rooks on the d-file are very
annoying, but if we sidestep all the
threats carefully, I think we should
still be fine.
I think we should still be fine.
Yeah, I'm going to try to bring the
magic here. I can't guarantee anything,
but
I will play my full strength. Not that I
wasn't previously, but
I'm going to try extra hard now to bring
out the GM magic.
I'm trying to figure out what we do if
white plays knight c5. That's a big
dilemma.
Goes c3, doesn't play it. Ooh, but c3
looks like a juicy
move, because we now have a3.
Ah, but white then plays knight c5.
But then we play ab. White plays rook
d7, play Queen a8.
It's terrifying.
It's terrifying. It's terrifying.
You can also play knight d6.
You can also play rook d6.
Tick-tock goes the clock.
Okay, we got to try it.
Man, this guy is good.
Okay, now I got to like super ultra
focus.
Rook d6 is an option here. Actually, not
a bad one, I think.
Mm.
Very, very hard to decide here what to
do.
I'm getting I'm getting soundly
outplayed. Let's go rook d6. Let's try
to take some pieces off the board.
He finds the move that I was afraid I
mean,
okay, takes, but still, I'm not entirely
convinced why this is bad for us. Rook
takes d2. I was expecting Queen takes
d2.
Now, I thought we go knight d6 and try
to re- rotate re- re- rotate the knight
to c4.
Now, I thought we ro- ro- ro-
rotate the knight to c4.
No, for sure. Okay, but b3, incredible
stro- very strong move, I think, to stop
knight c4, restricting our knight.
My gosh. Okay, what do we do now? I
guess now we play Queen c6 or Queen b6.
Okay, my intuition is to play Queen to
C6 in order to target the F3 pawn, which
is one of white's main weaknesses.
Okay, now our pawn on A3 is a big asset
for us because yes, it's a weakness, but
if white takes it with the king then the
A file opens up and that gives us
potential conditions for some cool
tactics.
So, I'm not necessarily going to go rook
A8 automatically if he goes King A2. I
am most worried about King A2. I think
that's a very very professional move,
which is not an obvious move I think for
most players to go after this pawn, but
of course it is for this guy.
E4 comes to mind trying to create some
counterplay.
Mhm.
Let's see.
Yeah, this this might be a
tough game to say, but knight B7
actually doesn't look half bad.
Knight B7 doesn't look half bad.
Yeah, let's go knight B7. Try to take
the knights off the board, exchange
white's strongest piece. Exchange
white's strongest piece.
Exchange white's strongest piece. Now,
King takes A3 is probably the best move
and the knight takes E5 there's Queen
takes E5.
Yeah, probably King takes A3 knight
takes E5 Queen takes E5
is one possibility.
Other moves are available in this
position as well.
Yeah, watch my accuracy be like 60% in
this game. No, I really don't think it's
60%. I think it's I think it's good.
I think I'm playing well with the
exception of A4, which was a big
mistake. Very instructive mistake, but a
big one.
Okay. Yeah, white is white is better for
sure.
White is better here.
But white is better, but black is very
solid. I mean, our king is not unsafe.
There is a move that I'm really worried
about. I won't say it just in case I'm
not
To be totally clear, I don't think our
opponent is stream sniping, but just to
be totally sure there is a move that I'm
worried about here and it's another
incredibly professional move.
It's a findable move and I I'm positive
he's going to find it, but
um
still I I want to
Okay, no, he didn't find it. He takes
B7, which is not what I was worried
about to be completely honest. I was
most worried about knight E4.
I was worried about knight E4 and yeah,
I blown into the Sorry, yeah, yeah. King
A3 knight C5 Queen C5, of course there's
Queen A6 check.
Uh winning the queen. Sorry about that.
I was only thinking Queen takes F3, but
then the rook hangs to check. It's late.
It's late. It's 5:00 a.m., so
apologies for that.
Yeah, this is an each Garry's training
account.
But this worries me a little bit less
because
now I think the position is close to
equal, maybe a little bit worse for
black, but I feel like we'll be able to
hold it.
Maybe not, though.
Maybe not.
Entirely possible that I'm like
mis-evaluating this and this was the
best line for white.
Okay, I think Queen C6 makes the most
sense here targeting the weakness. G3?
Jesus, this guy is good. Okay.
What do we do now? How do we play?
Queen F6 maybe is a very tricky move
here
trying to activate the queen through H4.
I really like the look of Queen F6
actually. I think this might be a strong
defensive move. We're trying to get our
queen active. Basically, my strategy in
this position with black is twofold. The
first is I want to provoke white into
taking A3. I think King takes A3 would
be a huge mistake here, but I'll explain
it later.
The second idea
that we have
is to bring the queen into the attack
via H4, which I think our opponent might
have missed. Now, Queen F2 is a big
threat as is Queen takes H2 and things
are getting very sharp unless
he he finds some crazy defense here,
which I don't see.
Fighting tooth and nail here.
Trying to gather chances.
Yeah, black is in trouble, but it's like
long-term trouble. It's not like white
threatens to win the game right away.
It's just the the long-term sort First
of all, the queen trade should be
avoided here at all costs. We should
never trade queens here because white's
going to put this pawn mass to good use.
A3 is going to fall in a rook endgame
and white's just going to create
connected passers. So, mental note to
self, do not allow queen trade under any
circumstances.
King takes A3
is possible, but is always going to be
met with an A file attack. Obviously not
right now, but I'm not worried about
King takes A3.
And we can also try to chip away at the
queen side. Yeah, one person in the chat
is suggesting a move that I have in
mind, which is Queen E2. We can play a
move like H5 and basically we can try to
perpetually weaken white's queen side.
Whoa, whoa, Queen B7.
That can't be the move, can't it?
Now, we can take H2.
Probably we should take H2. I feel like
this is
logical and now we have to figure out
where to put the rook. Probably we
should play
Yeah, my guess would we should play rook
F8 in order to bring this rook to a
secure square.
Rook E8 had the drawback of being a
vulnerable square for the rook. Now,
white cannot take on B5 because of rook
A8. It's not made, but it wins the
queen.
The biggest issue to me in black's
position is the fact that we have a four
on two on the king side, but but
it's hard to make a pass pawn out of it
and our king is also on that side of the
board. So, we can't just push our pawns
with abandon, whereas white
basically can. Like if white plays C4 at
the right moment, we might be screwed in
the long run, but man, if white goes C4
too soon, white could very easily get
checkmated here. So, I don't even know
that black is worse here. I don't think
black is worse uh from a practical
perspective. Whose king is safer? Oh,
it's impossible. Currently ours,
obviously. Currently it's ours,
but there's
you know, a counterbalancing factor in
that like we basically cannot put our
our pawn majority to good use at all
because the moment we play a move like
F5, everything opens up
and uh oh, it lagged there briefly. I
don't like that.
We cannot afford to lag out, that's for
sure.
Yeah, of course. Listen, we can sack the
F pawn to push the H pawn. The
The problem isn't in creating a pass
pawn, it's that when we create it, it
comes at great cost to the safety of our
king. So, for example, the moment we
play F5, the queen starts to make
contact with G7, so like the move rook
to D7 might lead to instant checkmate.
So, my strategy here with black is a bit
different. It's actually to go after
white's king and to set up checkmate
threats and threats of perpetual check
against white's king. I'm actually
forgetting for the time being about the
pawn majority
and I'm looking for moves that trap the
white king in something resembling
either a mating net or unstoppable
perpetual check.
And once you start thinking in that
direction, I think the move our opponent
might be worried about is Queen C2 and
he has good reason to be worried about
it because Queen C2 is a very deadly
threat.
And the reason it's a deadly threat is
because we're trying to get the queen
over to A1. That's a checkmating square.
But the additional benefit is that we
also have this check available on C1.
So, if after Queen C2 white plays rook
E3, we have Queen C1 check forking the
king and the rook. I don't see a clear
move here for white. Now, our opponent
is sinking almost all of his remaining
time on this.
Whoa, what a game.
It's going to be a lot to analyze here.
All right. Now, I'm liking this a little
bit more. He's down to 2 and 1/2
minutes. If he gets down below a minute,
I think we'll have good winning chances.
Like our opponent already can't do this
again. What he did here, take like 4
minutes, he can't do that again.
Yeah, so I'm going to
audaciously pour some more tea as our
opponent is thinking.
Yeah, so as some of you are pointing
out, it's not a disaster, but if you
play a move like Queen to G1, you let
the white king escape back to the second
rank. Now, in that case you could
deliver a check on F2, but why give the
white king more freedom than it needs?
Like the queen on H2 is genius because
it restricts the king as does the B5
pawn. So, it's a very unlikely pair.
But notice the cooperation between
between our three pieces, right? The
king, sorry, the rook, the the queen and
the B5 pawn. All of them are playing a
role
in boxing in white's king on A3.
The pawn is controlling A4, the rook is
indirectly defending the pawn and the
queen is cutting the king off along the
second rank making it very difficult for
white to even move.
Hopefully our opponent isn't like
disconnected or something.
He's down a minute and a half now.
Queen D5 is not obvious at all piggies
on the seventh. That is not an obvious
move to me. Queen E4
was the more natural move to me.
Now, I don't think that changes our
plans. I think we should still go Queen
to C2 trying to put a little pressure on
his clock. Now, very important, yes, I
see the alignment of the queens,
but obviously the rook has nowhere to go
with check. Rook to
E3, we have a draw in our pocket now. We
can give a check, but I think we can
play for the win here and I think right
now do not play rook A8 check because
that loses the rook with check, but
that's not the only avenue through which
we can involve our rook and we can also
play rook to D8
and I think we're winning.
I think after rook D8 black is winning
because we're threatening checkmate in a
couple of moves on D2.
If white blocks with his own rook, then
we have Queen C2 check forking the king
and the rook.
And if rook E2, I have to calculate
this, but I think rook D1 is winning.
Rook D1 Queen A8 check King H7 Queen E4
check, we go G6, we end the checks. I
think we can play rook D1 and I think
we've won.
And we strike first with mate. Let's go.
What a tough game. Queen A8 check King
H7 Queen back to E4, we cover with G6.
White runs out of checks
and white has no way to stop Queen A1
mate.
Whoa.
Yeah, our opponent played definitely,
you know, 23, 2400 level for sure and
that sometimes happens when players are
a little bit provisional
like and don't play quite as much,
but big big big kudos to our opponent.
That that was close. And in fact, the
last three games were all very close.
Okay.
A lot to unpack both theoretically and
and in terms of uh
what happened in the later middle game.
I know that I kind of sung the praises
of this line.
Our opponent ended up knowing more
theory than I did, but do give this line
a chance. I promise that it'll it'll
bring you a lot of success at at most
levels. Okay, so
Okay, so here's a little bit of of an
overview. Let's go to the main Najdorf
position. Remember that in our previous
game we faced the Canal Attack with
should be five check. And we ended up
getting into a similar structure to the
Najdorf because white later played D4.
You can watch that video separately.
Here we entered the main line Najdorf.
So a little bit of history. When was the
Najdorf first played and by whom? I
actually don't know the answer to that
question. Let me check.
And it's not necessarily Najdorf. Like
as I've explained many many times like
an opening isn't always named for the
first person to play it, although
sometimes it is.
Um it's often named for the person who
introduced the most
uh knowledge into the theory. It's
actually named It's actually first
played by Savielly Tartakower.
And Tartakower was a grandmaster
and a incredibly strong player and an
opening innovator. Tartakower was way
ahead of his time in his opening
repertoire. He would play one F4. He
played one B3. The guy was a genius.
Tartakower was the first to play the
Najdorf against Frederick Yates in 1926.
He lost.
And uh Najdorf
wasn't Najdorf didn't play the Najdorf
until 1939, 13 years after it had first
been played. It's just that he was the
most stable practitioner of the Najdorf
and he introduced a lot of ideas that we
now take for granted.
Just like the Alekhine wasn't first
played by Alekhine himself, but he kind
of played it with the most intention if
that makes sense. Okay.
Um so A6
why is the Najdorf such a scary opening
to learn? Well, largely that is based on
two things. Its reputation as one of the
most like crazy theoretical lines I
think stems from two important factors.
The first is Oh, wait. Let me open
another instance of the game.
The first is the
complicated nature of ideas across all
Najdorf variations and the fact that you
have to know a ton of different
structures and a ton of different
attacking ideas and you have to know
where to trade which pieces. So
strategically it's very complex, but in
terms of the breadth of theory, white
has literally like eight or nine moves
here that you have to know
to the teeth. You have to know it by
heart. What are those moves? Well, in
this game we face F3. Bishop to E3 is a
very similar move and often transposes
into the F3 variation if white drops the
knight back to B3. But here there is a
more positional line. There's knight F3.
There is bishop G5, which is widely
considered to be the most dangerous
move. It's also the most popular.
There is the Fischer Attack, bishop C4.
If caught unaware, this move can lead to
very quick victory for white. There is
uh the positional bishop B2 that was
favored by Karpov and Geller among
others. Geller.
There is H3, which became ultra ultra
popular in recent years and still
remains one of white's best weapons.
There's the slightly more obscure, but
still very topical F4. There is
Najdorf's favorite line A4.
There is bishop D3, which also got very
popular lately. And then there's like a
series of very provocative and rare
moves that still have to be studied. H4
I played myself in the US Championship a
couple of years back.
There is like A3 is a move I faced queen
F3 with black recently and didn't know
what to do. There's queen to D3. Against
Ray Robson I played knight to B3. And
it's not like if you don't know all of
these lines you're going to lose out of
the opening.
But if you want to play the Najdorf
well, you have to know all of these
moves.
So just
imagine the amount of theory that And
within each of these moves there's like
a gazillion sub variations. You have to
choose a line for black and you have to
study all of white's subsequent setup.
So it's
studying the Najdorf is a lifelong
undertaking, which is why
although I love it to death as an
opening, I just don't recommend it to a
lot of people.
If you want to take a crack at it, there
are, you know, I think there's a
Chessable course on the Najdorf.
But there's Anish Giri's Chessable
course on the Najdorf.
But it's it's a very very serious
undertaking. Just know that. Okay. So in
this game uh in this analysis we're
going to focus on the English Attack
exclusively with F3.
Okay, so we play uh E5. White plays
knight B3. And comparatively speaking,
this is a pretty narrow narrow this
narrow line. Um compared to some of the
other variations where white can deviate
like on every step, here there is almost
no deviations because
yeah, knight B3, bishop E6 is
essentially forced. Almost everybody
plays bishop E3 here. Bishop E7 is
fairly forced. And here queen D2 is the
only feasible move. There are some
obscure lines, but the important thing
to know, and I didn't know this, uh and
I lost to this as a 2100. I played the
immediate G4. I thought, "Hmm, well, why
do we need to play queen D2? Why don't
we just immediately uh it's like in
baseball, right? Getting the lead. Why
don't we get the lead on the king side
attack so that when black castles, you
know, we go G5 quickly. I'm such a
genius." Does anybody know
the actual reason that this is bad? And
there's a
delicious opening trap associated with
this. G4 is a big mistake. White to
play. Black to play and get a big
advantage.
Black to play and get a pretty big
It's D5. Very good. It's D5.
White plays G5 and you push D4.
White plays GF, you play bishop F6 and
black is better. I've won a couple of
games where white goes bishop D2 and
says, "Well, let's avoid our pawn
structure from getting ruined." This,
ladies and gentlemen, is one of the
quickest checkmates in the Najdorf.
I have won blitz games against title
players like this.
And so what that means is white has to
go
uh the other way. White has to go bishop
F2. Black plays D6.
You get into this end game. And
obviously this end game is better for
black. Material is equal and white's
pawn structure on both sides is
incomplete uh shambles. So just very
important thing to know.
G4 is met with D5. There is also the
move knight to D5 here, uh but I've
never been particularly uh impressed by
it. Black has many things that they can
do. I like just knight D5 EDN bishop F5,
which is a very standard reaction to the
move knight D5 in the Najdorf.
And then you often drop this bishop back
and start attacking on the king side. So
realistically queen D2 is the the only
sort of serious topical line. Queen D2
castles king side
and castles queen side. Okay, so this is
uh
starting off point for a a wild mass of
theory that is the subject of its own
books.
This position was first reached
in the year 1971.
The first person to reach this position
with black was Robert James Fischer
against Robert Byrne.
Fischer was the first to play this line
with black. And Fischer
this just tells you how ahead of his
time he was.
He understood that the correct move is
knight BD7.
He understood to play B5. And in this
position he made an inaccuracy, a move
that has fallen out of favor, which is
the move knight H5. The knight is very
awkward here, but it was played up until
the 2000s. The main line, as later
discovered, is to counter attack white's
knight with B4. Which leads to a wild
wild line. White typically drops the
knight back. White attacks on the king
side, black on the queen side, and you
literally get
chaotic, unexplainable, crazy amounts of
theory where both sides are like trying
to tear each other's throat out. Um what
you can do if you're interested in this,
you can very easily look these lines up
on on Lichess or, you know, on YouTube.
But
part of the reason I recommend A5 is
that it it it evades the madness of the
main lines with knight BD7 and and B5.
Uh this is totally brain melting and
it's not particularly instructive.
This is where I don't like the way that
some instructors present learning
openings. Like there are certain
openings where you will have to devote a
certain amount of time to memorization.
And the process of memorization is not
itself instructive. So people often ask,
"Well, I don't want to memorize because
that doesn't help me become a better
player." Well, you have to do it not
because it helps you be a better player,
but because it's a prerequisite to
playing certain openings. And this is a
great example of like where
you basically have to just memorize if
if you want to play this line. Just to
be totally honest. But A5 is a nice
compromise because there isn't quite as
much theory here. I think the ideas are
more understandable. And uh it's it's a
sideline, which means white is less
likely to know uh the best moves. This
was invented by a Hungarian grandmaster
Ivan Nemet. And it was played by a lot
of GMs in like the '80s and '90s and
then it gathered momentum into the early
2000s.
So we're analyzing the English Attack.
And the sideline I propose is A5.
Okay, so the most popular move is is in
fact bishop B5, which is what we faced
uh in the game, although it doesn't
score very well.
It does not score very well.
Um
just a second.
Let me make sure I'm involving the
engine here.
Just uh just to see what the what the
top Stockfish recommends
nowadays after A5.
Sorry. Give me a second. Of course it's
freezing as usual.
Typical. Absolutely typical.
Sorry. Hot second here. This is hard.
This is This is hard to even talk about
because there's so many moving parts.
And I want to try to remain instructive,
but there will be some theory that we
have to get through here.
Because I don't think A5 is is well
explained in in like chess literature.
So I'm going to give you some of my own
analysis.
All right. Let's see if Chessify works
this time.
I mean, even Hikaru I I don't think
would necessarily be very comfortable in
this line. Okay, so according to the
newest newest Stockfish, the best move
for white is actually to stop the pawn
in its tracks with A4.
And A4 is not an easy move for white to
make because it creates a major major
hole on B4. And this is actually how I
like to play here with black. You can
play either knight C6 or knight A6, but
I usually play knight to C6.
Okay, you might say, "Well, I get it so
far. You're trying to get the knight to
B4."
And once you get the knight to B4, not
only are you pressuring the C2 pawn, but
you're also in many cases preparing uh
D5. So, it's not enough for white to
know A4. White also has to know like a
crap ton of
uh supplementary theory.
Oh my gosh, my Chessify is just like
really struggling here.
Okay, so after knight C6,
white's best move is to play G4.
Black plays knight to B4.
And most of the online games that I have
uh in this variation
continue with with G5, which is also one
of uh white's best moves. And the
problem is that black is just not in
time
uh to play the move D5.
Now,
the line that I really like to play
online is to drop the knight back to E8.
So, what we're talking about here
is um white's best response to to the A5
variation, which is A4 knight C6 G4
knight B4 G5.
Now, if you run this position on the
engine, uh you will find that
the engine recommendation is to play
knight H5.
And the knight potentially can access
F4, but the cool move to play online is
knight to E8. And if white is caught
unawares by this move, my success rate
in this position with black is something
like, you know, 75%.
Because
well, if you're looking at this for the
first time, who can tell me like what
seems to be natural here for white? What
seems to be a natural continuation in
this position for white?
Yeah, so I mean, to me H4 seems to be
the move you play if you don't know
anything about the position because you
try to keep attacking.
So, H4 black plays rook to C8.
Now, again, you don't know anything
about the position, you probably play
H5. Black is already not worse. Here
black strikes at the center with D5.
I've had a ton of games that go this
way.
Now, what is the point of D5? Well,
black is trying to go D4.
And at this point, white cannot take
with the knight because he's going to
lose his queen. They're going to lose
their queen after rook takes C2.
Um so, white has to take with a pawn.
And this is the point. Now, the bishop
drops into F5 attacking C2 from a
different angle.
Okay, well, how does the white defend
this pawn? It's actually not easy to
defend this pawn. And the only move that
doesn't lose is knight B3 back to A1.
All other moves simply lose the game.
I've also faced bishop to D3 a bunch of
times. And here, you can trade and take
on D5 forking the knight and the pawn on
F3. White's position is collapsing.
There's a beautiful line where if white
plays knight A1 here,
black plays
well, that's not as beautiful of a line.
There's knight A2 check, and black
basically has a devastating attack.
Um white has to find the move knight A1.
And only now do we understand why we put
the knight specifically on E8 a couple
of moves back. We now involve the knight
via D6. We play knight to D6. And as it
turns out, this knight on D6 becomes
Oops, sorry. Becomes a very very
important attacker because it accesses
the C4 square, blockades the pawn, and
black has fantastic compensation for
uh for the sacrificed for the sacrificed
pawn.
That is the bottom line. So, for
instance,
after knight A1 knight D6,
white has a hard time finding a move.
Most people here, they try to go after
me on the king side with G6, but I just
play F takes G6, H takes G6, and you
could just take with the bishop. White
has no attack.
You can involve your queen. You can drop
the knight into C4. And black has
excellent long-term attacking chances.
Now, what most people do not know is
that in this position, white has a much
better move than H4. Grandmasters know
this, but you know, your average Joe is
is not going to know theory nearly this
deep. The correct move here for white,
which unfortunately does kind of bust
the line, is F4. F4 is incredibly
strong.
Because white is trying to drive the
pawn up to F5 and dislodge this bishop
from E6. So, black has to react to that.
If black plays E takes F4, white plays
bishop takes F4. And the idea of this
trade is actually very positional. It's
to get the the knight the D4 square in
the center. Oh, if black tries to do the
same thing and we play the move rook to
C8, black is kind of going to run out of
attacking firepower here. This is very
very technical, very technical. But at
this point, white can start playing H4.
And black is just not in time to create
counterplay. If we still try to play
this D5 move after E D5 bishop F5, this
is where white has that extra resource
that they wouldn't have in the previous
line. Who can tell me what this resource
is?
This is the reputation to the uh A5
variation in the way that I play it.
So, I mentioned this a little bit
earlier. It's not bishop D3. We already
talked about that.
Um why did we play F4? Think about it
that way. Why did we play F4?
So, there's two possible moves here. The
sort of thematic move is knight to D4.
And if we compare
uh in this position the H4 variation,
if we compare this position
with uh the position where you play F4
instead, so let me just click straight
into it.
In this position, you can see two two
chief differences. The first is that
white can now play D6 and trap the
bishop. But also very convincing is the
move knight D4, which hits the bishop,
protects C2, and black runs out of
active attacking ideas.
So, if you want to play this with white,
this is the best line. You want to go
A4. But I mean, this is like incredibly
esoteric, I would say, knowledge
comparatively speaking. And if you want
to play this with black, but you want to
know the best line objectively, which
keeps chances alive, it's actually to go
knight H5 here.
And this the position remains like
incredibly complicated. I was analyzing
this a couple of weeks ago, and after
king B1, you want to go F6. Things get
very advanced here, so I won't talk too
much about this line. I'm already boring
peo- people to death. But hopefully this
gives you a little bit of context in the
uh
uh in the
A5 line. So, in in this game, we face
the main response, which is bishop B5.
This is the most popular response uh at
a human level to to the move A5.
Okay, so A5,
let me just uh I'm also making these
moves in Chessify so I can tell you the
engine evals and stuff. So, A5 bishop
B5.
And now, of course, we play uh the
thematic idea knight to A6, getting the
knight back to C7.
Okay, so king B1 is a recommendation
from some old books, but I actually
think that black is totally fine here at
this point according to the engine.
Bishop B6, and now, of course, you have
to know the move queen to B8.
Um
and now we face bishop to A4.
And this was the first critical moment
where I couldn't decide between rook A6
and D5.
And D5 is actually the correct move. And
we're following a game between Peter
Svidler.
He Svidler. And Evgeny Najer from uh the
Russian Championship 2006.
This is the only game in this position
where D5 was played. In five other
games, rook A6 was played. So, both of
these moves are possible, but Stockfish
does prefer D5 at a very very high depth
here.
And Peter Svidler did take on C7, and
the game ended in a draw.
So, this is the moment where our
opponent deviated from theory by making
the mistake knight takes D5. And this is
a mistake according to the computer.
So, I won't talk too much about rook A6
other than to say that it's possible,
but let's focus in this game on the move
D5. So, I think our opponent just rushed
rushed in with knight takes D5 without
realizing that he's facing the the
massive problem of the B pawn advancing
to B5 and trapping the bishop. The
correct move here is bishop takes C7
queen takes C7.
Now, of course, white can already play E
takes D5.
And who can remind me how we would
respond to this move? Another important
idea that features frequently in this
particular line. Do we just move the
bishop? What do we do? Yeah, we play
rook FD8.
And now, a queen sacrifice that also
occurs in other lines of the knight or
white's best move, this was found by
Svidler, is D takes E6.
And after rook takes D2,
the position becomes wildly complex.
White plays E takes F7 check. Black
recaptures on F7.
And white takes back with the knight in
order to give the bishop an attacking
avenue via B3.
The engine evaluates this with a smidge
better for white, but largely it should
be a draw.
Black has enough activity here to keep
our king safe. We play rook to D8.
Svidler played A3. I mean, kind of
showing that he doesn't really know what
to do.
Black actually parked his king on G6,
which is not accurate according to the
engine. According to the engine, the
best move here would have been a weird
move queen C5, actually aiming for F2.
And the position is very double-edged,
but essentially balanced. This is an
important idea to know. Like, a lot of
top players have lost because this
sacrifice can be incredibly strong
uh in in a lot of different positions.
And I'm actually going to find a game
here really quickly.
If I remember correctly, it'll show you
a good instance of where this queen
sacrifice can be winning for white
and also winning for black.
Yeah, and and hopefully through through
the lens of this analysis you're
starting to understand like
this is one sub variation of a sub
variation of a variation of the knight
earth.
Right? And and we're like swimming in
complications and we're in a position
that hasn't even been reached before.
And still yet you have to know this
because this could very conceivably be
reached.
You're starting to see just the breadth
of theory that that that you have to
know and why why these things take
people like years to to actually learn.
And even then you don't like fully learn
it.
Okay, so
I actually was wrong. White ended up
losing this game which is good. White
was
I don't you know I don't love showing
Karjakin games.
But but still with our primary motive
here is to provide instructive value. So
there was a famous game. This game was
very very popular at the time that it
was played. It was Karjakin against
Anand in Wijk aan Zee 2007.
And in that game
in that game
uh Viswanathan played the main line.
Here he played knight BD7 and they went
down the sort of the main path.
92 98. This is the crazy line that I was
talking about except Karjakin played H4.
And Viswanathan played A5 King B1 Knight
B6. I'm quickly going to get to the
critical position. They were making
moves blah blah blah D5 and guess what
happens here. Bishop takes B6 Queen
takes B6 and if you're paying attention
then you should know the course that the
game takes. Karjakin takes on D5.
Viswanathan pins the pawn.
And uh Karjakin he first played Bishop
C4.
The knight hits the pawn and Karjakin
decided at this point to sack his queen
with D takes E6.
Rook takes D2 E F7 checking H8 Rook to
two with a crazy position that is
approximately equal which Viswanathan
won in the end. So this queen sack
exists in several different variations
of the English attack. This game was
like very hotly debated and analyzed
when it was played because the knight
earth was like huge at the time.
Our instance of this sack is pretty
similar and also leads to a complex
position. But our opponent of course
plays knight takes D5. So let's
uh focus on that move instead.
Okay, so we play knight takes D5 and the
engine already shows a winning advantage
for black in this position. The question
is what did we do wrong because clearly
I messed this up. You will not believe
this.
You will not believe what the top engine
move is after Queen F2. I can give you
five attempts collectively as a chat to
find the engine's the like strong
engine's assessment here.
But there is also a move that makes a
lot more sense to me which is also very
difficult. Oh, what an incredible idea.
So the top
the top suggestion is H6.
Just rubbing it all over white's face
that
that they can't do anything here.
But the second engine
recommendation is gorgeous and also
leads to a winning position for black.
It's the move Bishop to D8 which I saw.
This is a sensible idea, right? You
force the trade you have to take. And
well what do we want to do here? We want
to go B5. Why did I reject this? Well, I
rejected this because you're giving
white a tempo. What can white use this
tempo to do? Well, we already know that
this becomes a big problem because this
allows the bishop to evacuate via B3.
But what's incredible is that in this
position black is not obliged to
recapture.
And black has the ridiculous move B5
right away.
Now you're like my head is spinning. I
don't know what's going on. Black is
completely winning here.
And here's the reason why.
Both bishops are hanging.
Let's consider the options of moving
both of them. If white moves the bishop
from D8 then it's all very very simple.
B takes A4 knight C5 and of course there
is this fork knight C3 using the B file.
If white tries to desperado give give
away the other bishop
it's essentially the same thing. I mean
black plays Queen takes B5. Now white
has to move the bishop from D8. And it's
the same exact thing. Black plays either
A4 or rook even rook FC8 is very strong
because the attack on white's king is
going to be completely unstoppable. Like
all of the pieces are just converging on
white's king.
So just
I saw Bishop D8 but B5 was completely
not on my radar. And what's so
interesting about this is that a couple
weeks ago
Yes. A couple weeks ago
I did a lecture at the chess camp that I
was teaching in in Atlanta on avoiding
autopilot moves. And I identified like a
couple of instances where autopilot
moves are the most common. And one of
those instances is automatic recaptures.
So one of my like biggest takeaways from
that lecture was avoid automatic
recaptures because you never know when a
tactical opportunity can uh manifest
itself.
And the game that I showed to to
illustrate
that concept was a Capablanca game that
has nothing to do with the topic at
hand. But just to show you really really
quickly what game I I chose to
illustrate that.
So it was the following game. This is
going to be a long video.
So I will not be offended if you go to
bed or you don't
remain for all of it.
I promise.
All right. So here is the Capablanca
game that I showed to illustrate this
concept.
The point is this. In this position
Capablanca takes the pawn on B7.
And black plays Bishop takes knight on
F4.
And obviously the the autopilot move
here is to play GF.
But then I'll I'll kind of give you the
elevator pitch here. Black is able to
reach a drawable end game. So you have
to say wait a second. Is the recapture
forced?
Once you realize that it isn't you're
able to find a sequence of really really
pretty in between moves.
Who can come up with the winning idea
here for white? This is a great exercise
for you to train your advanced tactical
awareness. If you're watching on YouTube
you start with rookie one check.
But that looks like a blunder because
black can cover with the bishop.
And now you strike with D6 check.
The bishop is pinned. The queen is
pinned. The king can't take because of
rook D1.
If the king steps back black gets
checkmated here with Queen B6 and rook
C1.
And if the king moves forward then the
queen retreats to B3.
Again if the king takes then rook C1
wins the queen.
If the king goes to F5 there's check
check.
Um and here Capablanca wins with check
check
and win the queen. Because if black goes
the other way if black goes to H5
there's G4 and Queen H6 mate. All of
this had to be calculated by Capablanca
when he played rookie one. In fact when
he played Queen takes B7.
So
long story short this is a well-known
situation in which our brains are often
incapable of even generating uh an
alternative to the automatic recapture.
And the more like natural the recapture
the harder it is to find a move like B5.
Which show you that blind spots persist
all the way to GM level. It's totally
natural to have these blind spots and
you shouldn't feel that you know I have
it all figured out tactically. This is
instructive for for me as well. So that
was our big mistake. I played rook A6
which to me is a much more natural move.
Um but this relinquishes all of the
advantage.
This relinquishes all of the advantage
and after rook A6 the evaluation
according to the engine
is only a small advantage for black.
Actually now it's showing basically
equality.
Okay. So that was the missed win. We
play B5 white plays Bishop takes E7.
Here I did see the possibility of B
takes A4 because it's another capture.
And after B takes A4 the position that I
was struggling to evaluate is Bishop
takes F8 A takes B3. Like how on earth
do you evaluate a position like this?
And the evaluation is actually equal.
The move that I was worried about is C4.
Which is a crazy move. It counterattacks
the knight and I was worried that
black's attack fizzles out. Now you guys
should understand that in such positions
you almost never want to play pawn takes
pawn because white is going to use the
umbrella method and just hide behind the
pawn. By keeping the pawn on B3 you're
opening yourself up to many more
attacking options. So here the correct
move is to play knight to B4.
Threatening like a smothered mate. White
has to take that knight.
And now black throws in an intermezzo
forcing the king into the corner.
Because if the king goes the other way
if the king goes over to C1 then you
play B takes A2 and the pawn is
basically unstoppable.
Now you play AB threatening checkmate on
A2. White has to go A3 and the attack is
unstoppable after pawn takes pawn.
You're threatening to take on B2 and
play rook to A2 check
and to and to win the game with a
straightforward
uh straightforward attack. Very very
simple.
Nothing particularly complicated in any
of these lines.
But because I was totally unsure of how
to evaluate this position I decided to
err on the side of being more
conservative. And so I I decided just to
grab the bishop on E7 and play this
position. Probably a mistake in
retrospect
because according to the engine this is
a very promising position for for black.
White has to play the calm Bishop C5.
Black plays BC.
Of course King takes C2 is out of the
question. And here white black plays
rook C6. I did see this position in my
mind and also didn't know what to make
of it.
Apparently in order to keep equality
white has to counter sack the exchange
and go rook D1. This is just engine BS.
I don't think anybody would play that.
Rook C1 is a mistake because of Queen C8
creating the hidden threat of Bishop F5
pinning the queen
to the king.
And if white moves the king into the
corner then suddenly knight before comes
with great effect because if white plays
queen A4
who can answer the following question?
Can
black play rook takes C5 why or why not?
The H6 business
that that move that the engine mentioned
H6 I think it's just like a preliminary
luft move because bishop D8 will be
coming next. Yes, you can take on C5
because at the end of the line you can
block with the queen and reach a
technically winning end game with two
pieces for rook. Ridiculous levels of
tactical complexity all of this hinges
on these like minute details
and that's what makes this opening so
exciting but I decided to avoid this
particularly because I would we were in
time pressure at this point.
So knight takes E7 knight to C5
only move rook to C6 which is I think
totally natural bishop B3 and the engine
gives equality here. Bishop takes B3
A takes B3 rook F to C8 attacking the
knight and amazingly knight to E7 is
actually the only correct move. I have
to give our opponent massive kudos
because I was expecting knight to D3
but after rook takes C2 just so you know
the engine eval in this position and if
you're watching on YouTube you should
pause and try to evaluate this position.
Like do you think black is slightly
better? Do you think it's equal?
What is the actual evaluation here?
So it's winning for black it's plus
three
and the reason it's plus three as I
explained during the game is that the
king is essentially weak forever.
Even if it hides on B1 black is always
going to be able to play A4 and open up
the queen side. BLACK'S KNIGHT has
tremendous prospects in the center. So
you go knight F5 the king has to escape.
Now you make some luft with H5 just so
there's no back rank problems
and white's rooks are also kind of
biting on granite particularly the one
on E1.
Then black is going to go knight C4
black is going to go A4 and you are
eventually going to get to this king.
So I don't want to give get too
technical here because we have more
stuff to talk about but definitely in
this
position we would have taken on C2 and
the queen is much much better than these
two rooks because of how exposed
white's white's king is.
Okay?
So knight to D7 is correct.
Amazing.
Black plays queen to C7
and white plays rook to D2. He has to
defend the pawn on C2.
Now we played H6 which the engine likes
it's one of the top moves just making a
little bit of luft. White plays rook H
to D1
and here a very fateful moment where I
made a very big mistake. A4 is in fact a
big mistake. After B4 it's plus over
minus black is in serious trouble after
I made that move.
The correct move here would have been in
fact the immediate knight F5 as like I
had indicated during the game trying to
get the knight to an outpost on D4.
And now the engine line is crazy. It
goes G4 knight D4.
Now white to play and find a pretty
simple tactic. Who can spot like you
know pretty stock tactical move here
that leads to liquidation?
It's yeah knight takes E5 removing the
defender.
Now you can achieve a draw several ways
with black you can play queen takes E5
or you can counter sacrifice on B3. This
is a desperado
and it leads to a liquidation. Takes
takes takes takes and finally the smoke
clears and it's basically a draw because
the position is like largely
symmetrical.
So that would have been a natural
conclusion to the game. Instead I played
A4 overzealous forgot that white gets
this evacuation square not just any
evacuation square.
You know it's like a helicopter that
flies to evacuate you but it's like a
Ritz Carlton hotel room inside that
helicopter. So once the knight gets to
C5 it's like a permanent outpost and
then the rook dives into D7 and black is
suddenly in big trouble. Here I found
the only move that doesn't lose on the
spot knight F5.
Our opponent plays the move C3 guarding
the D4 square and now A3. Once I
realized that I was in trouble I knew
that I have to play very very actively
in order to generate concrete
counterplay.
And after knight C5 yet another very
very difficult decision and here I made
another mistake. After rook D6 white's
position is technically winning.
Although the mistake started to come in
bunches here G4 is also inaccurate.
White should have simply played B takes
A3 and black has essentially no
compensation at this point for the
sacrificed pawn. White dominates the D
file and black is running out of ideas.
What would have been the correct move
here and why did I not play it? Well the
correct move would have been A takes B2.
Why didn't I play that move? What was I
scared of? Well I was scared that the
rook would infiltrate D7 and that my
queen could potentially get trapped and
in fact it does get trapped if you play
queen B6 there's a rook B7
and if you guys want to see a beautiful
line
here black has a devilish defensive
resource.
Let's see who can find this resource but
then who can also find white's response
which keeps the queen trapped?
This is a very very difficult move
but you can try to guarantee the queen's
safe passage to D8 by playing
not rook A8 because here you play rook
B6 this is an empty check and white wins
but rook to D8 which is a hard move to
wrap your head around. Like wait what if
white just takes the queen? But now you
take the rook with check and remember
white can't go up to C2 and attack the
rook because because you're going to
promote. So white has to waste time
taking you take on B6 and you have two
rooks for the queen. Position is
unclear.
But white does not have to engage right?
You don't have to respond to the email.
White doesn't have to engage. White can
just go rook G1 or rook F1
which is another hard move to see
because you just leave the open file but
black's queen remains trapped. Now the
rook is in the queen's way.
Don't have to respond to chat exactly.
So therefore what that means is that you
have to go the other way you have to go
to B8.
And what I was worried about here is
that white would essentially checkmate
us on the F7 pawn. I saw this move and I
like crap my pants because queen to D5
is a huge threat.
Our pieces are super passive and
according to the engine black can hold a
draw here but with some crazy ideas like
black has to find this move. I already
did not see this move because from a
distance I thought that there was a
fork.
How could I have missed the simple rook
takes D7 queen D7 queen A8 only move
defending the rook attacking the knight
and black is somehow surviving walking
the tightrope and actually winning in
this position.
So after rook C7 black is only slightly
worse.
Just ridiculous and not particularly
instructive so let's actually get to the
game rook to D6.
Here G4 kind of gave us a new lease on
life because after rook takes D2 I think
what our opponent might have forgotten
about is that queen takes D2 allows the
knight to jump to H4
attacking white's only pawn weakness on
F3 and therefore keeping the material
balance. So white was forced to take
with the rook but now the knight is able
to potentially access the C4 square
which which means B takes A3 is no
longer good here due to knight C4. That
is the difference right? That is why
white should have taken immediately.
Here if black plays rook takes D2 the
queen captures on D2 and keeps the
knight out of commission. The knight is
unable to access this outpost because
white dominates the D file forever.
Okay?
So subtle difference here therefore
white was forced to change their plans
and play B3.
But now with the A3 pawn comes long-term
counterplay
and I played queen C6. Our opponent very
professional king A2 knight B7 and this
is I think the final critical moment in
the game. I think this is the moment
where white missed his last chance to
get essentially a technically winning
position.
So our opponent traded and it's still
better for white but it's very very
unconvincing. The correct move here was
a difficult one to make. Who can tell me
what it is?
Who can tell me what the correct move
is?
It's knight C5 to E4.
And the point of this move as my coach
would say is to play for domination.
This is a hard concept for a lot of
people to understand and I think
this position is a great window into how
players of different levels approach the
same position. So let's take three
levels like beginner level intermediate
advanced and my point is never to like
denigrate beginner. I think in in fact
it's the contrary it's to show like what
you have in store for you.
So I think a newer player would look at
this and say okay well
the knights are are facing each other
but I don't really see the benefit of
trading on B7 so let's just take
It's not a free pawn because black has
knight takes E5.
And if the queen recaptures then black
wins the queen which I missed during the
game.
But that's not even that important
because if the pawn recaptures black
plays rook A8 check king B2 and after
queen to A6 black gets a devastating
attack down the A file. So in fact white
has to leave this pawn on A3 using the
umbrella method. An intermediate player
would operate like our opponent did and
say okay well we have to trade knights
because otherwise we lose the C3 pawn.
So let's trade knights and play a
general improving move just to defend
the C3 pawn. Okay this is an advantage.
But a grandmaster would say okay the
knight on B7 is on the worst square
of the entire chessboard.
And this is an opportunity for white to
assert complete positional dominance by
playing knight E4.
Notice the role played by the G4 pawn.
It prevents black from playing F5 and
pushing away the knight. The knight on
B7 cannot rejoin society in any
meaningful way.
Black has no moves and no ideas. You can
try to take a pair of rooks off the
board,
but after the rooks are traded and white
plays queen c5, black is just
collapsing. The b5 pawn is ultra-weak,
a3 can now be captured, and black's end
game is dead lost.
So, I can probably find examples of
moves like this if I look hard enough,
but I've talked for long enough, so
I'm going to I'm going to run a quick
search and see if I can find a similar
idea.
Let's see.
b4
So, black has an idea on b7.
Yeah, I definitely there there are
actual examples of like moves like this,
but I'd have to look a little bit harder
to
uh to to to to actually find a
meaningful example.
Yeah, I'm I'm seeing a lot of examples
of this move being played,
but the basic idea is to play for
domination.
Um and to use your pieces to restrict
the mobility of your opponent's pieces.
94 is
an incredible move, and it just shuts
down all of black's ideas. Probably, I
would even play a move like rook a8 here
and try to grovel.
And here,
it's actually not so easy for white to
finish black off. Like, you want to
improve your position slowly. Rook d3.
Black has nothing better than to
shuffle. Now, queen d2. It's very
instructive to see how the engine wins
these types of positions very patiently.
Rook d5. Nothing crazy. Just like moves
that step by step induce a weakness. And
now, you go queen d3 and you win the b5
pawn. Like, black collapses on one of
several fronts.
And this is because the b7 knight is
totally out of the game. And that is a
series that I want to do at some later
point. Like,
get a bunch of players and compare how
they approach the same position. Thank
you, SlimG, for the sub. In any case,
after the trade of knights, I think
black has excellent practical chances to
save the game.
And obviously, we ended up winning the
game. And we won the game really because
of the mistake I made at the very end.
Rook d3 queen f6. Notice what I'm doing.
I'm not even trying to defend this pawn
because I understand that anytime white
takes it, we can give a check and swing
the queen over, and the a-file attack is
at the very least going to give us
practical compensation.
What I'm trying to do instead is seek
maximum activity for my pieces. How do I
approach that? Well, there's two forms
of activity. There's one that comes from
attacking your opponent's weaknesses.
This is what I was trying to do on c6.
And then, the other form of activity is
essentially infiltration. You're trying
to detect which avenues you can take for
your pieces to
aim to infiltrate the enemy territory.
So, in this case, there's only one
avenue. When you see this pawn
construction, you know that there are
some dark square weaknesses, and so
that's how I was able to find this queen
pathway to h4. Just trying to get the
queen as active as possible.
And after queen f6, the the engine
already throws equality. It's already
equal.
Queen e4 queen h4.
Queen b7 is another mistake, and now
black is better.
Here, black is already better. So,
white's last chance to maintain the
balance would have been to drop the rook
back to d2.
And the game continues. But here, our
opponent lost the thread. Queen b7 queen
h2 king a3 rook f8.
And um already, it's almost impossible
to defend this
without uh
without an engine. Queen e4 queen c2.
It's still not losing for white until he
played uh the panic move rook e3. There
was an only move here that's almost
unfindable, and that is c4. And this
gives white chances to hold the game.
Black is only slightly better
because if black plays queen b1 to
threaten checkmate,
you don't go queen e2. That blunder's
made in one. You go rook d2, and somehow
white is still holding on amazingly.
Check rook b2
because the queen holds the a8 square.
According to the computer
What a move! There's queen e3 here.
THAT'S THE TOP engine move.
Queen to e3.
Are you freaking kidding me? And you
need to play this move only after the
white rook gets to b2
because it deprives the king of the
escape square.
Ridiculous.
This is checkmate on the next move.
But white is able to hold by playing the
incredibly calm rook b1,
renewing the threat of queen takes e3.
Black can check on a7. Black can check
on f2. So, the attack continues.
The attack rages on,
but black is not like winning by force
here.
After king a3, rook d8 is winning
because of this uh idea, but white has
to go king c3. So, at some point, the
position becomes indefensible for a
human. And most of these positions that
involve a permanently weak king like
this are impossible to defend unless
you're Magnus Carlsen or you have or
you're Stockfish or you have 3 hours on
your clock and can't blame our opponent
for missing rook d8. I think what
happened was he was fixated on
preventing rook a8 and forgot that there
are other avenues, other ways to get to
white's king. So, ultimately, we end up
striking first. And here, our opponent
resigned because the checks run out very
quickly, and there is no way to stop
queen a1 checkmate.
Oh my god. What a ridiculously
complicated game with so many different
stages.
So, a couple of takeaways if I could
even
dare speak in those terms.
So, in this game, we followed the
English attack. I don't know if I'll
repeat the Najdorf again just because
this was a crazy undertaking.
We focused on the English attack, and we
focused on the sideline a5,
evading the main line, which goes knight
bd7 and then b5.
So, the point of a5 is to push this pawn
up to a4. We'll probably get a chance to
play it again.
What I didn't talk about here is moves
that are not bishop b5 or a4. And
there's plenty of those moves. Like,
king b1 is a popular move here, and
black is in fact supposed to push the
pawn all the way up to a3 and induce
weaknesses. But I think we've had enough
theoretical uh exposition for one day. A
lot of like newer players go g4 here
because they don't really sense the
danger inherent in pushing the knight
away to a1.
And here again, you play a3 and then
knight a6 knight b4 followed by d5. It's
this like typical idea.
So, I showed you what the best line is
in my opinion, which is a4.
Then, we looked at the actual game
continuation.
We saw that our opponent's main mistake
was knight takes d5. Instead, bishop c7
leads to a wild unbalanced position.
We understood that rook a6, as natural
as it is, was a mistake. Bishop d8 and
b5. Avoid autopilot moves is a good
takeaway from this particular segment of
the game.
Then, things were relatively tame until
the knight landed on d7. That's when
things got crazy again. We looked at
some cool lines. I made a very serious
mistake in playing another autopilot
move, a4. I thought this was good based
on general principles, but I didn't stop
to consider what b4 gave our opponent,
which was this massive outpost on c5.
Then, black's position becomes very
dire. I make another mistake in playing
rook to d6.
Then, another series of inaccuracies,
particularly knight b7, which would have
allowed knight e4. Here, white is still
winning.
But once the knights are traded, black
was able to find counterplay. We
activated our queen. We got the queen
into the attack. Forced the white king
to take the poisonous pawn and
ultimately used multiple directions to
finish off the attack.
Crazy game, and I know if you're
watching this on YouTube, first of all,
thank you for making it to the end.
This was all over the place.
Tons of complexity, but
this is a taste of what
of why chess is like a ridiculous game.
Because because this is just one tiny
corner of one tiny line of one tiny
variation, and this already
can be analyzed for 10-15 hours. This
game that this line.
And the Najdorf is one of the openings
that opens the Pandora's Box because the
position is so unbalanced
and with opposite side castling, by
definition, you get complexity because
both sides are
attacking and defending all at the same
time.
And so, structurally, tactically, the
positions are wild, chaotic, and can be
studied for many, many years.
So, if you want to open that box, then
play the Najdorf. Look at Anish Giri's
Chessable course. That would be my
recommendation. It's pretty accessible,
relatively speaking. But for newer
players, that is why I recommend a more
uh relatively speaking tamer Sicilian
such as the Accelerated Dragon, which is
easier to understand and easier
to learn.
All right, guys. On that note, I'm going
to head to bed urgently because I have
titled Tuesday in the morning, and I
don't want to miss it.
I'll be doing it in Russian in the
morning and then in English in the
afternoon.
I hope you enjoyed the game. I apologize
for all the long-windedness and uh
you know, if if the theory was too much,
but
I'm just honestly trying to give you a
window into what chess looks like at
this level without sugarcoating it. And
I There's nothing I hate more than
people pretending that it's all very
easy or that memorization isn't
required. This is what you're going to
have to do if you want to hit, you know,
22-2300 rapid, and
you know, this work has its redeeming
components as well.
Thanks, everybody. See you guys later.
Goodbye.